Finding Aid for Glenn Ruggles papers, 1880s-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Glenn Ruggles papers 1880s-2011
Ruggles, Glenn.
2 linear feet
2010223 Aa 2
Glenn Ruggles is an oral historian based in Walled Lake, Michigan. His collection consists of audiocassettes, photographs, and supporting material from his oral history projects.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Glenn Ruggles (donor 10436 ), in several accessions beginning in 2010.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Glenn Ruggles was born in 1930 in Grand Blanc, Mich., and spent his early youth in Oakland and Macomb Counties. When he was 14 the family moved to a farm located six miles from the village of Elk Rapids on Grand Traverse Bay. His deep love and appreciation for a sense of place have origins during these years. Following military service Ruggles earned bachelor's and master's degrees in history from the University of Detroit. For the next 35 years he was a history teacher in the Walled Lake Public Schools, introducing thousands of students to the excitement of discovering their family heritage and its place in the history of their community and state.
Beginning in the 1960s Ruggles began crafting a compelling approach to bring history alive. He utilized people's personal memories and rare historical images to tell the stories of bygone eras and vanishing places, writing a total of nine published books on aspects of Michigan history.
In collaboration with his colleague Fr. Bob Humitz, Ruggles also worked with the media of film. Their three films utilize oral history interviews and historical and contemporary photographs to bring history alive.
In addition to books and films, Ruggles has directed a number of oral history projects that did not directly lead to publications.
In 1979 Ruggles joined other leaders in the field to establish the Michigan Oral History Association. For over twenty years he participated in numerous ways to advance the mission and goals of the association. His contributions included serving on the board of directors, editing the association's newsletter, and presenting numerous workshops, seminars, and conference presentations.
Condensed from nomination package for Historical Society of Michigan 2011 Lifetime Achievement Award.
The collection is divided into series corresponding to particular oral history projects, followed by a Personal series and a Collected materials series.
Voices on the water: an oral and pictorial history of Antrim County's chain of lakes was published in 1998, with a second edition published in 2005. The series contains recordings of oral history interviews conducted in the preparation of the book along with photographs: original and copy prints of vintage views, some modern views, and snapshots of interviewees.
The library has release forms only for the interviews with Jo Anne Beemon, Warren Daane, Lena Stalker, and Byrnece White.
Subjects:
Anti-Catholicism--United States--History.; Antrim County (Mich.); Elk Rapids (Mich.); Knights of Columbus--History.; Ruggles, Glenn.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Antrim County (Mich.); Elk Rapids (Mich.); Ruggles, Glenn.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Photographs.
- Voices on the water (published 1998)
  - Photographs and papers
    - Moving North (Box 1)
    - The Chain (Box 1)
    - The Back Roads of Antrim County (Box 1)
    - The Villages of the Chain (Box 1)
    - The Lumberjack--Jess Letherby (Box 1)
    - The Resort Owner
      - Bill DeFauw (Box 1)
      - Chet Maltby (and miscellaneous Antrim photos) (Box 1)
      - Carolyn Shah (Box 1)
    - The Fisherman
      - Gertie Barber (Box 1)
      - Mike Huntley (Box 1)
      - Thale Yettaw (and Mary Kay McDuffie) (Box 1)
    - The Homemaker
      - Mae Fitzpatrick (Box 1)
      - Amy Smith (Box 1)
    - The Scientist
      - Richmond Brown (Box 1)
      - LaVerne Curry (Box 1)
      - Bill Weiss (Box 1)
    - The Poet--Terry Wooten (Box 1)
    - The Businessman
      - Guy Dean (Box 1)
      - Lyle Paradise (Box 1)
      - Harold Wilke (Box 1)
    - The Summer Resident
      - Warren Daane (Box 1)
      - Ellen Moore Poulson (Box 1)
    - The Preservationist
      - JoAnne Bier Beemon (Box 1)
      - Harry and June Janis (Box 1)
      - Warren Studley (Box 1)
    - The Farmer
      - Ben and Bob Samels (Box 1)
      - Byrnece White (Box 1)
      - Doyle Willson (Box 1)
    - The Teacher
      - Floyd Gregory (Box 1)
      - Lena Stalker (Box 1)
    - The Historian--Mary Kay McDuffie (Box 1)
    - Captions and completed (Box 1)
    - "Important" (Box 1)
    - Lumbering (Box 1)
    - "Must Use" (Box 1)
  - Slides
    - Antrim County's Chain of Lakes, Oral history interviewees, Outhouses (Box 1)
    - Brief history of Antrim County (Box 1)
    - Changing character of rural America 1948 (Box 1)
    - Island, Noble family, Sawmill, Lumberjacks, Camps (Box 1)
    - Old Elk Rapids, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Oral history interviewees (Box 1)
  - Audiocassettes
    - Barber, Gertie, 12/1/1990., 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Beemon, JoAnne 5/20/1996 (Box 2)
    - Brown, Richmond 10/28/1988 (Box 2)
    - Curry, Dr.[side 1], Mom [side 2] (Box 2)
    - Daane, Warren 8/30/1995 (Box 2)
    - Dean, Guy 8/24/1986 (Box 2)
    - DeFauw, Bill 4/15/1993 (Box 2)
    - Fitzpatrick, Mae 6/23/1995 (Box 2)
    - Gregory, Floyd 8/25/1988 (Box 2)
    - Huntley, Chas. "Mike" 9/23/1996 (Box 2)
    - Janis, June & Harry 5/19/1995 (Box 2)
    - Kirkpatrick, Walter 9/9/1997 (Box 2)
    - Larsen, Helen 9/9/1997 (Box 2)
    - Maltby, Chet 8/12/1986 (Box 2)
    - McDuffie, Mary Kay 9/3/1987 (Box 2)
    - Morrison, Beulah 12/19/1993 (Box 2)
    - Paradise, Lyle 8/23/1987 (Box 2)
    - Poulson, Ellen 7/13/1986 (Box 2)
    - Rode, Pat 11/2/1995 (Box 2)
    - Samels, Ben & Bob 2/13/1987 (Box 2)
    - Samels, Ben & Bob 4/27/1991 (Box 2)
    - Shah, Carolyn 12/19/1993 (Box 2)
    - Shah, Carolyn 4/19/1993 (Box 2)
    - Smith, Amy 5/8/1987 (Box 2)
    - Stalker, Lena 9/18/1994 (Box 2)
    - Stalker, Lena 7/12/1995 (Box 2)
    - Studley, Warren 2/13/1987 (Box 2)
    - Studley, Warren 4/9/1995 (Box 2)
    - Weiss, Bill 2/14/1994 (Box 2)
    - White, Byrnece, 3/21/1997., 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - White, Versil 2/15/1994 (Box 2)
    - Wilke, Harold 6/22/1995 (Box 2)
    - Willson, Doyle 12/20/1993 (Box 2)
    - Wooten, Terry 8/10/1987 (Box 2)
    - Yettaw, Thale 9/2/1987 (Box 2)
- Elk Rapids: the first hundred years (published 2007)
  - Copy of book (Box 1)
- Personal
  - "Elk Rapids Et Cetera" local history columns (Box 1)
  - Historical Society of Michigan 2011: Lifetime Achievement Award nomination package (Box 1)
- Collected materials
  - Fraudulent Knights of Columbus oath: Copy of oath document with commentary by Ruggles (Box 1)